Guide to the James G. Needham papers, 1884-1957
Needham, James G. papers, 1884-1957
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
James G. Needham papers, 1884-1957
21-23-479
James G. Needham, 1868-1956
6 cubic ft.
Letters, legal documents, diaries, scrapbooks, photographs, course materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence and documents describing the career of James G. Needham.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
James G. Needham was born on March 16, 1868 in Virginia, Illinois. He studied with John Henry Comstock at Cornell University, 1896-1898. From 1898-1907 he taught biology at Lake Forest University and then returned to Cornell as assistant professor of limnology. In 1914 when Professor Comstock retired, Needham succeeded him as head of the Department of Entomology at Cornell, a position he held until his retirement in 1935. He published numerous scientific articles, educational papers, and textbooks; he also wrote poetry and philosophical writings. Memberships included the Entomological Society of America, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the Limnological Society of America, and other scientific societies.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence pertaining to the taxonomic study of dragonflies; correspondence, typed reports, and printed material pertaining to the organization and administration of the Department of Entomology at Cornell; Needham's log of his trip to China (1927-1928) and papers concerning his teaching career and educational philosophy; extensive correspondence with American and foreign scientists, former students, and friends and family, concerning description and identification of insect specimens, publication of Needham's books and articles, establishment of the Okefenokee Society, attempts to get gasoline from the rationing board during World War II, tax matters, alumni activities at Knox College, accounts of friends' collecting expeditions, acknowledgments and remarks on his printed work, both scientific and literary, the purchase of land in Michigan, the establishment of Reed College, recommendations for students and friends, the creation of an Inter-American Wildlife Preserve in British Honduras (Belize), and his PLAN FOR PEACE; course outlines; class schedules; lab worksheets; field trip instructions and assignments; diaries and address book; logs of collecting expeditions; scrapbooks and photograph albums; including photographs of China; glass plate negatives; notes and manuscripts of Needham's writings; price lists of collections; lists of publications of Needham and others; pencil sketches and pen and ink drawings of insects and of a proposed limnological field station on Cayuga Lake; oversized geological survey map of East Ithaca, New York; diagrams of orchards and geodetic survey maps of pond and lake soundings; maps; and printed matter on a variety of subjects. Also included is correspondence of C.P. Alexander, George T. Atkinson, Liberty Hyde Bailey, Nathan Banks, Philip Calvert, T.D.A. Cockerell, John Henry Comstock, Thomas A. Edison, Alice Ferguson, Mrs. Leonora K. Gloyd, David Starr Jordan, Mrs. Elsie B. Klotts, M.A. Lieflinck, B. Elwood Montgomery, Edwin Mumford, Ira La Rivers, F. Ris, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Theodore Roosevelt, Will Sargent, Ernest Robert Tinkham, Henry K. Townes, Minter Jackson Westfall, Jr., and others.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Needham, James G. (James George), 1868-1956.; Needham, James G. (James George), 1868-1956. Plan for peace.; Alexander, Charles P.(Charles Paul); Atkinson, George T.; Bailey, L. H. (Liberty Hyde), 1858-1954.; Banks, Nathan, b. 1868; Calvert, Philip.; Cockerell, Theodore D. A. (Theodore Dru Alison), 1866-1948.; Comstock, John Henry, 1849-1931.; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931.; Ferguson, Alice.; Gloyd, Leonora K.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931.; Klotts, Elsie B.; Lieflinck, M. A.; Montgomery, Basil Elwood.; Mumford, Edwin.; La Rivers, Ira, 1915-1977.; Ris, F. (Friedrich), 1867-1931.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Sargent, Will.; Tinkham, Ernest Robert.; Townes, Henry.; Westfall, Minter J. (Minter Jackson) 1916-; Cornell University.--Dept of Entomology; Okefenokee Society.; Knox College--Alumni and alumnae.; Reed College (Portland Or.); Inter-American Wildlife Preserve (Belize).
Subjects:
Entomolgy--Study and teaching.; Education--Philosophy.; Limnology.; Entomologists.; College teachers.
Places:
China--Description and travel.; Belize.; Cayuga Lake (N.Y.).; Inter-American Wildlife Preserve (Belize).
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Diaries.; Scrapbooks.; Drawings.; Negatives.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Available Copies:
Letters from James Needham to Hortense Butler Heywood are photocopies. Original letters to Heywood are located in Special Collections/Archives, Parks Library, Iowa State University.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Boxes 1-3, 8
Series II. Miscellaneous
Boxes 3-4, 7-10, mapcase
Series III. Photographs
Boxes 5-6
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1888-1890 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1892-1894 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1895-1896 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, 1923-1925 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Log of China Trip, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Log of China Trip, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Log of China Trip, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Log of China Trip, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Log of China Trip, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letters of Condolence A.B.T Needham, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence re: Lectures, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Letters to Annabel, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Letters to Annabel, 1940-1945 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Condolence Letters, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Condolence Cards, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Undated Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Undated Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Charles Darwin Letter, No date (Folder in Ms. Box 16)
  - Greeting Cards (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Greeting Cards (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Greeting Cards (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Greeting Cards (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - To Anna Taylor, 1890 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - To Anna Taylor, 1891 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - To Anna Taylor, 1892 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - To Anna Taylor, 1893 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - To Anna Taylor, 1894 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - To Anna Taylor, incomplete, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - To John Needham, from father and mother, ca. 1931 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - T. D. A. Cockerell's correspondence, 1899-1912 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Additional misc. correspondence, 1905-1919 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Series II. Miscellaneous
  - Honors, 1913-1955 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - China Miscellany (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - China Miscellany (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - China Miscellany (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Taxes, 1908-1953 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Taxes, 1908-1958 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Financial (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Natural History of the Farm (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - West Virginia - Report, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Mexico Trip, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Cayuga Indian Festival, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - West Virginia Biological Notes, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Mexico and California trip, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - University of Puerto Rico, 1930-1935 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Apalachicola, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Laguna, 1922-1923 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Stanford University and Texas trip, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - San Clemente, 1923-1924 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - California Limnology-Elsinore, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Stanford Correspondence, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - West Indian trip, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - North Carolina-Kentucky trip, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Florida, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Flying Trip, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Olympic Mountain trip, 1942-1958 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Cape Fear River trip, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - North Carolina Collectin trip, 1929-1935 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - "Jingle of the Jungle", No date (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - California Limnology-Elsinore, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Santo Domingo, 1930-1947 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Cuba, 1936-1939 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Utah, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Okefenokee Swamp (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - My 75th Birthday, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Manuscripts, 1917-1918 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Ontario Manuscripts, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Ontario, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Ontario, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Undated Manuscripts (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Undated Manuscripts and Notes (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Undated Manuscripts and Notes (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Undated Poetry Manuscripts (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Undated Manuscripts (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Undated Manuscripts (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Undated Miscellany (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Undated Notes and Coreespondence (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Undated Miscellany (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Undated Miscellany (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Undated Miscellany and notes (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous Fragments Undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Writings by others (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Overpopulation (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Clippings about Needham (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Clippings about Needham (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Clippings about Needham (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Clippings, 1989-ca. 1947 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Miscellany (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Needham Publications and Advertisements (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Programs and Reviews (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Address books (Box 7)
  - Diaries (Box 7)
  - Book of place-cards, Jugatae Banquet, 1931 (Box 7)
  - Certificates (Box 7)
  - Passport (Box 7)
  - 88th Birthday book (Box 7)
  - Photo-scrapbook album, W. Virginia, 1930 (Box 7)
  - Indian Museum work, 1909-1910 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Peking Society of National History, King Senior medal certificate, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - "Check-list of Odonata of Oceania", by Erich Schmidt (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Dragonflies Manuscript, 1895 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Accounts, 1886-1892 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    -contains a dairy titled "The Diary of a Pedagague", starting on page 140
  - Miscellany (Box 9)
  - Maps (Box 10)
  - Key to autograph New York State maps showing watercourses and wetlands (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Finger Lakes Region (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Genesee Valley (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - #129, top of #153 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - #16, 17 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - #27-29, 39-43, 50 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - #51-56, 58-59, 62-66 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - #79, 80 (2 parts), 81-83, 85-89 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - #101-108, 112-113, 124-125 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - 126-129, 130 (2 parts), 131-134, 145-150 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - #151, 153, 155-159, 166, 171, 175 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - #176-181, 193 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - #206-207 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - #35,100-101; 122; Adirondacks (Map-case Folder 2)
  - Pinar del Rio [Cuba], 1935 (Map-case Folder 2)
  - High School diploma of James G. Needham, Virginia, Illinois, June 15, 1884 (Map-case Folder 1)
  - J.G.N.'s Bachelor of Science degree from Knox College, Galesburg, Illinois, June 11, 1891 (Map-case Folder 1)
  - J.G.N.'s Master of Science degree from Knox College, June 15, 1894 (Map-case Folder 1)
  - J.G.N.'s Doctor of Philosophy degree from Cornell University, June 16, 1898 (Map-case Folder 1)
  - J.G.N.'s Certificate as Phi Beta Kappa alumnus member by action of Delta Chapter of Illinois, May 11, 1917 (Map-case Folder 1)
  - J.G.N.'s Honorary Doctor of Letters degree from Knox College, July 18, 1921 (Map-case Folder 1)
  - Anna B. Taylor's Bachelor of Letters degree from Knox College (Map-case Folder 1)
  - Illustrated plates used in Needham's books (Box 11)
- Series III. Photographs
  - Alabama (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Archbold Biological Field Station (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Bass Biological Laboratory; Buildings at Englewood; Bethany Beach (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Beaufort Harbor Biological Lab." (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Biological Field Station (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Branch, Hazel E.: Photo portfolio of "Limnology class, Spring of 1919"; 4 loose pictures of specimens (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - British Guiana [Surinam] (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - China (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - China (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - China scenes (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - China scenes (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Chinese students (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Chinese students and families (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Chinese students and families (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Chinese students and Staff, with Needham, Peking (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Chinese students with Needham family, Shanghai (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Colleagues and friends (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Colleagues and friends (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Classes [?] unidentified (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Comstock, Anna (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Comstock, John Henry (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Comstock Hall (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Dynamite (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Family photo (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Family photos (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Family photos (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Family photos (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Family photos (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Family photos (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Family photos (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Field Trips (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Field Trips & Classes (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Friends & Colleagues (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Hilliard, Annabel, 1956. Constableville, NY. (sic) Thanksgiving 1956 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Indian Pageant on Beebe Lake c. 1914 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Knox College (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Lake Laboratory at Juanita Island, Lake George (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Limnology classes (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Minnesota (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Miscellaneous people (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous photos, scenes (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous photos (some identified) (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - J.G. Needham (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - J.G. Needham (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - J.G. Needham & students (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - J.G. Needham & former classmates (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - "Pamp" (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Photographs, Miss Swanson [M. Eurdloch?] (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - "Photoprints of entomologists from Dr. Matheson [?] 28 v.'45" (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Plants, shells, etc. (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Postcards (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Postcards, China (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Postcards, China, etc. (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Postcards, Malaya (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Postcards, Singapore & Penang (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Scenes (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - West Virginia (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - "Wild Flower Reserve & Ringwood" (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Willard Culver's photos. Englewood, Fla. June 1944 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Glass Negatives (Box 6)